video all right so we are going to
install a tool probably the most
universal tool for converting from
markdown into HTML and the purpose for
this is so that you can see the
association between markdown and HTML
very specifically that's the reason we
want to be able to see the two and how
they go with each other the tool is
called pandoc so you can search for it
it's called pandoc right here does many
many other things besides the the thing
that you you know may want but for this
purpose we're just going to get this one
thing so click on install pandoc
download the installer for Windows or
Mac if you're on Linux you already you
know how to do all this stuff you
probably don't need to do that um let's
see here so we want to get Windows I
think I'm on we going do the MSI that's
the auto installer uh again you should
already have install permissions on your
system uh did it make it let's go see if
it made it okay there we go I accept the
license is open source um install for
all users
install and this is going to put pandoc
the pandoc command onto my computer
hopefully uh why is the setup wizard not
happy there we go
yes all right so all right apparently
it's on all right now once it's
on if finish okay once pandoc is on um
we are going to check to see if it can
be executed um this what you're seeing
now is VSS code we talked about that in
another video and you open up this VSS
code and here we have some markdown this
is all covered in other videos and we
are going to open the terminal for the
first time um you may have seen other
videos about how to do with the terminal
you may have seen me doing the terminal
uh Windows terminal preview and all of
that for now for now let me put this
right there please be
patient um I as of this moment I think
the best experience for the terminal for
the user for the first time is in the
either the Mac terminal or the windows
terminal that comes with the system so
you can understand uh the terminal
command line that exists on the system
we are going to do lots of other videos
about how to put bash on your system and
use a different terminal and use a uh
you know just get in general get really
good on the command line but for today
we have one goal and one goal only I was
a little lary even going this early
because somebody's going to run down the
terminal you know Rabbit Hole too early
on me but right now the focus is on
being able to run that program from the
command line uh so that we can convert
this markdown into HTML that's the sole
purpose of this for this moment um yeah
the vs code terminal needs to mention
and that's what we're going to do so
we're going to go under View right here
and you can see the terminal you can see
the the the the fast and quick key which
is what I almost always use the control
left bracket in this case and we're
going to turn the terminal on and now
you're going to see the terminal Now by
default on Windows the terminal is I'm
going to get rid of my face here the
terminal on Windows by default is
Powershell uh it used to be dos actually
uh Powershell is a very important
terminal uh should you use learn it yes
you should learn Powershell eventually
it's actually required if you're going
to do cyber security uh but we will not
be covering Powershell in the Boost
because it is kind of a
specialization uh whereas I believe
understanding the terminal in general
and specifically The Bash terminal is
more of a universal skill in my opinion
so we're going to be focusing on that
but for right now you don't care so
let's talk about what this is this
terminal is a command line what does a
command line even mean so a command line
is we'll talk about it in another video
as well but I'll say it here this is
telling you what hard drive you're on
and this is a Windows path note the back
slashes it's that's how you know it's
windows and it's it's got a prompt and
you over here you can type things in you
can type date again we'll talk about
this uh someplace else there's lots of
commands over here uh you'll notice that
some commands are now involved that that
were not here LS didn't used to be here
dir is still there you're going to learn
all those commands don't fress don't
stress about it right now I wonder if it
has clear it does it does have clear
nice um but if this works uh so let's do
LS well I wanted you to see this okay so
look at here here we have the index on
HTML page that's listed over here in our
Explorer and we have the sumd file which
is also right here it tells the length
and everything when they were modified
and their permissions we we you'll
understand all that eventually but for
right now I just want to show you that
you can see the same information in two
different ways graphically or from the
command line using the terminal so now
we're going to see if we have the the
pandoc command over here so let's do
pandoc uh how about Dash let's just put
a-h and see if it finds it okay pandok
can't be found it does not know where
pandok is uh and I was afraid of
this um it's probably not in the path
when we installed pandoc it put it in a
special place and as we might have to
actually type all of that out um so
let's see if we can find it um uh it's
actually not in the path I think we
actually have to put it into the path um
I don't know let me let me try one other
thing here let's see if we can just in
the search bar here with the windows key
if I type pandoc let's see what happens
nope it's just got the installer okay so
so I was afraid of this we we this is
why I don't want to do terminal stuff
too early but we're going to do it
anyway um when you install a command
line tool you have to use the command
line tool where it is and so I don't
even remember where the installer put it
uh but it's definitely someplace on our
system so we need to go find it I did
you guys notice I could go back and
watch the video um but I mean I know a
bunch of commands I could use to find it
right now but I'm kind of hesitant to do
that uh let's actually try it with the
oldfashioned Explorer pretending you
don't know how to use the command line
tools so let's go into the seedr drive
this PC uh here's the C
drive and we'll see here Windows users
program files so it's probably in
program files again it's a different on
window on uh Mac of
course um and there's pandoc okay so
there we go there's the pandoc
command um I think that is probably we
could probably actually move it um I
wonder if we could actually just copy it
in here wouldn't that be interesting if
we could do that I'm going to try it I
think you can copy it
in that would be cool oh my God we we
actually copied a binary this file is
not a text outut editor open anyway no
we don't want to open that normally you
would never put an executable into your
directory like that but let's do that
let's go ahead and do that just for fun
just so the file is right there for now
for now for now we'll we'll get rid of
it later but now when we do an LS we
should probably have it there oh my god
look how big that file is in fact if you
do LS DH I think it makes it human
readable no ls- Capital H nope okay well
LS on pandoc is I mean on uh on pan po
shells not the same as bash for sure um
all right so here we have pandok we have
a a program uh let's see if it works now
if I type pandoc will it see it it does
see it um the Pand command was not found
it does not see it h what if I do this
instead type do/ Pand can I do/ pandoc
like
this oh seems to be doing something
about we do SL can you. pandoc I I like
forward slashes better oh I did it okay
good all right so let's let's like make
this bigger so we can see it it can
scroll up if you want but normally you
can't see all that look at all those
commands we don't need to know all of
that all right so again I'm kind of I've
got mixed feelings about this we changed
the order of how we do this normally you
would learn the term in the previous
years you learned the terminal all that
stuff before web stuff so you would
you'd already easily be able to do all
these commands um but for this time
we're pretending you don't know any of
that and so you install pandoc put the
executable there and now let's actually
try it so pandoc we're going to use
forward slashes because that's more
Universal um and then we're going to run
it against the file we're going to do
sumd and see what happens oh look what
it did we ran it and we got output and
it showed us the program
right um now if you want to learn all
about pandoc and kind of get your sense
of how to deal about commands you can
only where I told you look at the dashh
you can go look at all this stuff but
for right now you don't really need to
stress about that the only reason we're
doing this right now is because we want
to uh see what happens when we convert
something from markdown into HTML that
is the purpose of this of getting pandoc
uh so if you feel I'm going to say this
again if you feel a little bit stretched
if you feel like you know downloading
and installing pandoc is hard it's good
practice to install things you have to
have admin access to do that if you feel
like going and finding the executable
and putting it in the same directory
right now is hard you know gives that
some practice these are those are more
or less basic computer skills and and
then running but but right now all we're
going to do is we're going to run the
program and we're going to use it to
make a new file and the syntax you're
going to what I write is you're going to
have to memorize it you will understand
that after the fact but for right now I
just want to the missing piece is we
need to make that conversion okay so
let's go back to it let's so we're going
to say pandoc what is the dot about what
is the slash about don't worry we'll
talk about that later so pandoc and then
we're going to do su. MD and um there's
we're going to do uh a a greater than
sign and then we're going to do um sum.
HTML right
and now we have look what it did it made
us a new file that's HTML you see what
it
did right it made it it made it made it
didn't do all of it though it just made
part of it so we took the markdown file
here and we can see that it got
converted into this you see how that
conversion happened all right now there
is one other thing about pandoc we can
do I have to go look it up actually um
where let's let's so uh let's pipe it
into more I think there's a more is
there a more maybe there's not uh if
that happens by the way if you get stuck
just do control
C all right so pandoc dhore there we go
that gives us so it stops it on the page
we're going to cover more later when we
learn the terminal so format it tells
you what type output file data
directory uh if you don't want to do the
the you can do the d o file if you want
to have it be to a file
um what I'm looking for there we go
Standalone see this Standalone
thing uh Standalone equals true or false
we're going Standalone makes it into
more than just a little snippet the
snippet is nice though because why what
is the snippet do the snippet shows us
exactly what it translated to and we've
learned about unordered list last week
uh and other times but now you can see
that Association why is that valuable
because when you do that here so like
you can click over here but in terms of
learning you don't know this is actually
HTML but you can't inspect it you can't
see it but by running it through pandoc
you can see it and so you can you can
learn about HTML and markdown by looking
at the markdown and then seeing how it
produces HTML seeing what it does okay
so let's actually experiment with
something else here let's go back up I'm
pushing the up Arrow we're going to go
back up to the up arrow to the Pand
command that we did that made this right
we learned by reading we learned by
reading the document here that that we
can do- file that means that we can
instead of that if we wanted to we could
do- o file right and it'll do it um but
let's try it with uh let's see if that
works so uh that'll make us a file again
same exact thing as before just a
different way to write it um we used uh
in uh redirection in the other one but
let's says let's add- s too because we
know now that it's got Standalone I
wonder if- s is enough to do it if we
do-s uhoh it says this document format
requires an unempty title element
defaulting to Su as the title to specify
a title blah blah blah we don't care
about that but here's something
interesting look at our HTML file now
see what I'm saying now you kind of see
the
difference this is why we did this and
this is also a great segue into CSS
which we're going to be covering in the
next video so uh we're going to start
covering CSS so once you have pandoc
installed I want you to see that you can
convert between this into this in one
command pretty damn cool right by the
way if you close this it's still there
you can go back and do view terminal and
it still be there it's just a way of
temporary closing it if you want to if
you're getting tired of doing the menus
you can just do alt back slash or
whatever in my case is control back
slash alt back you see what I'm saying
and that hotkey is right here control
back slash uh and you can go back and
forth so and you'll get good with that
you'll be pulling the terminal up a lot
um and as you can see though when you
make a standalone web page it produces a
lot of stuff here right isn't that crazy
you know what's really cool about this
let's go preview it remember down here
remember down here in the bottom right
we have the port it says Port 550 Z we
can go back to our web page that we were
using to preview and now we can add on a
URL path we can do
slash uh what do we call it sum sum.
HTML sum.
HTML and did I say back tick yeah and
and there it is this is a paragraph look
at that look at how clean it is in fact
we learned about inspect element last
time inspect element you can see that
this is my dark reader stuff but you can
see how you see what it did here right
now I think this is interesting because
if you look at the one that we wrote
from scratch which is this one right
it's considerably different and one of
the reasons for using pandoc is it does
a bunch of
rendering um so it you know it changes
it gives us a bunch of things that we
can now play with right in fact it gives
us an
entire uh set of of class classes by the
way another reason to do this instead of
using inspect element is because you get
a bunch of extra crap in here a lot of
times and you don't always want to look
at that because some of it's added by
the server and different thing this way
by using pandoc we can see exactly what
was rendered so this turned into this
but if you don't want the whole page
once again I'm going to show you uh the
very first one get rid of the S if you
get rid of the- s because you just want
to see how things uh
relate right that warning was whoops I'm
doing I'm doing Linux stuff um look at
this so if you want to see how they
relate to one another you can do this
and by the way this we're going to use
this to do some pretty funky magic later
in fact let me give you a little preview
of The Magic we're going to be doing uh
just so you can see how stinking cool
that is so uh which Pand let me make
sure I have pandoc on here this is you
don't know anything about this yet but
you will all right so let's say I'm
writing let's say I was writing like
food. HTML and you might not do this but
let's say you were doing this I could WR
uh here is a thing um yeah one uh two
right and uh something let's say that I
just want to convert maybe I want to
even write some HTML here maybe I wanted
to do some math Jacks which we talked
about before I can actually send those
two lines to mark down to pandoc and
render them in line just by sending them
to pandoc and then having those lines
replaced with the what came out of
pandoc pretty damn cool right I can
convert the whole document uh using the
same method I'm G to send it to pandoc
and that'll whoops I didn't do the whole
document uh pandoc and we send the whole
thing and it converts the whole file uh
I could send the whole thing and do Pand
do-s and I can create an entire thing
and now I just created an entire
document by just sending it to the
outline H the reason I'm showing you
this is because somebody out there may
be wondering I mean this goes this this
is a thing watch I can I want to just
change this one line pandoc
whoops uh I can CH send just this one
line uh to pandoc and it will convert it
and I'll get my em stuff there so you
might want to just do some conversions
but I'm using what's called Unix filters
and a lot of people will reach for
plugins and things uh I in my opinion
too early because they could have used
Unix filters and one of the most
powerful Unix filters is pandoc that is
why we're learning pandoc because pandoc
shows you the conversion whether it be
for just a segment of something or for
an entire file you can go back in here
and there's so many other reasons to use
pandoc uh not to mention you know
publishing and all the other stuff that
comes with it but pandok has is a very
amazing way to preview how most markdown
would be rendered and the default
version of pandoc which is called pandok
markdown is relatively close to get a
flavored markdown so so it'll be you
know consistent with other things that
you will be learning if you're wanting
to know what all this other stuff is in
here that we're going to cover in other
videos um right we are learning HTML and
CSS directly we already did that we did
that last week we learned HTML here
directly to write HTML and then we
learned uh we're going to be learning
CSS next but the reason that we
introduce pandoc into this is for you to
help understand why what the association
between HTML and pandoc is and I'm going
to say it again it is as important for
you to learn markdown as if not more
important than to learn HTML uh you need
to learn HTML but from a practical
perspective you're not going to be
spending very much time writing HTML in
your Tech Career uh unless you go into
web development of some kind um most of
the time you're going to be
manipulating uh HTML that's been created
for you by some other tool and web
developers are going to come unglued by
my saying that but that's the truth the
truth is is that the Practical skill
that's required for the job is
understanding how to write markdown and
maintain it and and understanding how to
read and comprehend markdown and occas
I'm sorry HTML and occasionally CSS but
the the the daily job to write HTML and
CSS does not exist unless you're you're
in a web de development role primarily
uh almost all the time you're going to
be writing markdown so that's the reason
we're doing the pandog thing those are
all very legitimate honest questions
have fun with that and uh next we'll be
taking care and looking at CSS